With programming it's a...
you can do whatever you want.
And at some point you, it's...
Um, I wouldn't say biblical, but it's like
there's nothing in the beginning
Or, or just as you have in history
it's just an empty space
and you can start throwing things in there.
Well, what I want to do when I,
I want to program like I can think.
So like ten years ago I painted a lot,
and I want to get the same feeling with code.
Programming is like a superpower.
There's so many things that you want to do
that you could do by hand
and it would take you a long time but if,
like, programming just increases your capabilities
you know, almost exponentially.
I've always been fascinated by computers.
I think Jobs, quite, is particularly interesting.
You know, saying that computers
are bicycles for the mind.
You know just a human on it's own is just a human.
But with the addition of a bicycle
we'll become the most efficient biped out there.
And the computer I think holds
the same thing in terms of
the possibilities of what we can do with our creativity.
And when you have that computer to support you
you can create incredible things.
I addicted myself.
And, I'm highly addicted to programming.
You can't stop me, sometimes I forget to eat.
Sometimes I forget to sleep.
And...
I don't know, can you turn a pickle back into a cucumber?
Probably not. So I'm here for life.
You've got me, it's terminal.
You are sculpting possibility space.
Which sounds big, but in a way that's what it is.
You're adding with those little lego bricks
of code and language that you have.
Put them together and you add more possibilities.
And with every new brick, basically
your possibilities increase, uh, many times.
And that's, in a way this adding and taking away,
that's kind of the design process now.
It'sÉ I still feel in control.
Uh, but I like to be surprised.
I think that's the beauty of it.
Um, the thing when a system goes beyond
what you naturally understand it to do.
And sometimes you have something that surprises you.
And I always look for that, that one moment, basically.
In my practice as an artist,
I've always been interested about the universe
and the scale of the universe that's around us.
Especially in comparison to us.
And, uh, and I think kind of the commercial work that I do
it's really about trying to take people into the moment.
I'm really trying to get people into that kind of feeling
where you're not thinking about your past, or your future.
That you're really in the now.
[clears his throat]
I dream in code.
One time I woke up and I said:
Rebecca! What time is it?
And then I said:
I think it's January 11111111111!
Like that.
In 1999, I was making out with my girlfriend
Anne Marie
and I fell asleep because I was very tired.
And I could see the function with a block of code
with if then statements and for loops
describing the, um... the kiss.
I think, coding and technology in general
informatic technology is the thing
that defines our time right now
and as an artist, I feel like
my job is to explore this stuff that defines our time right now.
Not the stuff that defined our time 100 years ago.
So, I just got into it naturally.
You know we have people who write demos in 256 bytes.
These are 256 numbers strung together
to create an image or an animation
and everyone goes WOW, how did they do that?
And this is incredible, because the way actually
you can only achieve this by
knowing every single bit about the technology underneath.
Knowing what command to use in which position
so you can actually reuse the code as data
to create something else.
And it's incredibly cryptic
but it shows incredible mental strength
and intelligence
to actually achieve something  like that.
Like it's a way to interface with these things
that's on a very basic level of the way that we
you know, process our experience.
And I think that's like a big problem with software.
It's so abstracted on so many levels.
You know data on it's own is just noise.
If no one processes that data it's meaningless.
It's really just dust, you know?
And that's what I really find interesting about the demo scene
because it's actually, people are really focused
on producing such compressed
versions of information.
Not data. Code is information.
It's not random noise.
That information can actually create a physical
emotional feedback in the viewer.
And I find this really incredible.
And the code is so microscopic
it can be easily shared.
And it was like, um, I liked it visually.
Just because of the shapes you got.
But I also liked it in a sense of, um
...experimenting.
So it was like, I couldn't do this with actual water in a tank.
But here I can do it on a smaller scale.
And, just imagine what it might look like.
There's a guy I know who made this project
it was just these strings in a box, and it was called Wiremap.
And you were able to present like, 3D objects inside it
like dynamically, using these really cheap materials.
It was really inspiring, it was like
a video projector, which you can get ahold of
almost anywhere now, and some strings in a box.
But all the string's like perfectly laid out,
so each one of them casts, catches
a different column of pixels from the projector.
So I started recreating this project and I worked
a lot in like how to make it more advanced
in terms of the algorithms behind it.
So there's now an interest in really thinking about interface.
So on one hand that's quite interesting
And then, but I think what's more exciting is that
uh, is the people hacking them.
And that those communities are going to
discover actually the more interesting things.
I think you get to a point in large visualizations where
it's just actually too much data to look at as a flat image
and you have to do some sort of zooming or
you know, flying through navigation to get
I don't know, to focus on some small part of it
because it's, there's so many examples of this like
huge hairball of connections
and like it means nothing, at some point.
And he is basically explaining
how the database works
and he says there's one point here,
and then you go around and then there is another
audio sample there, and another one there
and because this is closer this is the
one which is matched.
[laughs]
And he explains everything like that.
I think like for a little while people'd still be
doing this thing with augmented reality
where they'd get like an iPad out and
they'd put it in front of something.
but that's just ridiculous.
It's never going to be like that eventually.
It's all going to be about like,
you go around the world
and things happen that
couldn't have happened before.
You can see something.
I mean you might be looking
over here and you might,
this thing might pop up that says
here's a read-out from this thing.
And it'd be perfectly rectified
to the way you're looking at it
but somebody over there won't
be able to see it at all.
But you won't be wearing anything. You'll just be,
your environment is having this light cast onto it
because it's being scanned
and projected onto. And, uh
I think that's like, that's gonna be really interesting in the future.
It's very difficult to take your mind
out of what you are living
where everything is already so fast
and there's always a new app and and a new,
a new innovation and something you want to try
because you just read about it so
also the information like circulates so fast that
yeah, it's um... it's really difficult
to project yourself in the future
because you feel almost like you are already
living in some kind of future.
Even if you fantasize about having
a more powerful laptop.
Interviewer: "Is there an experience,
a digital experience, that you desire to have?"
Oh yes, tele-transportation. Yeah. That's a, that's
there are many things,
Yeah, there, there are many things, OK.
Some I shouldn't talk about.
But yeah, tele-transportation, it's because,
you know there was a time when they would say
well with video conferences you won't need
to meet, but they don't work so well.
You still need to be with the people, to really
discuss and work on projects.
You can do part of it by video conferences,
but it has its limits, so it means I have to travel.
I am sick of traveling. I waste so much time
in the airport, and waiting for trains,
and I cannot work, so, I wish tele-transportation
Is it, is it possible? Is it going to be possible?
I really want that.
You could start off with the point cloud of this.
And then, I don't know, at some point when I say
talking about water or physical systems
all the points could just flush, or
or turn into water,
or something like that. Just to
illustrate the thing you've been talking about.
The footage is frameless, so because this
footage is rendered in a 3D environment
and you have to look at it from some perspective
you can browse anywhere in it
you can see just edges of it,
or potentially multiple people
you know like floating heads or whatever,
can be in the same space
or having a conversation that never happened.
Or objects can come in,
or parts of things can be taken out
um, that can illustrate what they're talking about.
Or even simpler things like that, like
the faces can fragment,
or um, the colors can change.
Or the camera angle can change even though
this camera's been completely static.
There's just a lot of room to play.
It's an experimentation.
You don't know what will work. There's no
cinematic language that has evolved yet
so we're sort of at a point to define that.
[quiet overlapping voices]
It's the thing that comes after a video camera.
It's the thing that comes after a camcorder.
It's a Kinect with a digital camera on it,
I guess there's a sound microphone.
And there's this amazing blinding light.
I mean we definitely are stuck in that paradigm.
We're stuck in the mirror world, you know.
Like, I look at this, and I do this, and stare
at myself in the screen that's like in here
you know, so that's an issue.
Andï¿½ I don't know how you could fix that.
This is still a camera
it still has all of the like, dynamics and
kind of set up that a camera makes, so
and like the politics of
the camera world, you know
I wouldn't want to have that inhibition there.
I wouldn't want to have it sitting there
and reminding me to like, look at the image
the way that the camera looked at it.
I mean, if that's 3D, then let's turn it inside out.
Let's look at it from behind.
Let's break down the image that you get.
For me, I perceive a continuum between
abstraction and figuration.
I see a place all along there where there's a lot
of really interesting places to go
that communicate with us
in so many interesting ways.
And seeing a host of new aesthetic approaches
coming into wider use
And seeing the very sort of non-photorealistic
aspects of that film
that sort of made me excited for what
we can accomplish if we just sort of
don't worry so much about duplicating reality
and figure out how to create kinds of images
that have never been seen before.
Further into the future I think we could
probably see autonomous cameras
Cameras that can hover, or move on their own.
And paint areas, creating you know
large sets of data
that you choose camera angles
out of after the fact.
And, uh, do my own performance,
and then blend that
with the existing point cloud
that you give me
so that I'm doing an additional
layer of extemporaneous performance
which moves and changes.
One me this month, one me next month.
And maybe another me the month after.
And have a different algorithmic
treatment per word.
But I just want to try and explore
every path that it opens
And see what connections we can make
and how we can build on that.
I hope there are no limitations and
I don't think there will be.
The only limitation is time,
and we probably won't live to
see things we would think
is a limitation right now.
But I do think it gets more and more complex
And it's, I mean, it's such a young medium
as well. And it's evolving so fast
All this computation and power, I mean we...
if you look at where we are with our tools
that we have available , um
we've got the basic needs covered.
The basic input, output, interaction, rendering
That's, that's done. And people
don't predict big advances there.
There's the limit of our physical senses
is kind of the limit of where real and virtual
kind of overlaps and meets.
That's visible.
I mean, Tim Sweeney from Epic Games says that
in 2020, at that point in time we'll have
graphics cards producing,
and 3D game engines producing
visuals that can fool our eyes believably enough
and, so all this extra computation power
from then on hopefully will be spent on
developing deeper knowledge systems
that can do something like
modeling consciousness, or create more
complex, deeper interactions.
And I think that's where
I'd love cinema to go to
where we can play with these virtual actors
and we can interact with them
on a believable, deeper, human level.
Hopefully it'll all resolve into
one big noble conversation.
And there you can definitely
see the cumulative effects
of you know, an internet which is, or a network
rather, of millions of neurons.
Kevin Kelly's observations of the complexity of
the entire sphere of connected, um, computers
is approximately right now on the order of
the same size as a single human brain.
And it is going to become
very interesting when that
becomes a hundred million
times more complicated.
Um, and that will be like
the greatest network ever built
and certainly we'll be able to do
some very interesting things
Um, I think of it as kind of the world
becoming one mind.
I think it's going to be more like that,
than sort of the computers taking over
and, you know, Skynet.
Um, but maybe I'm an optimist.
Of sorts.
You always feel this layer of artificiality
which I'm, I'm...
I never managed to truly engage and feel comfortable there, so
um, so yeah, a virtual version world would
be good, but ones I've tested so far have not
I don't think they can replace physicality.
Doesn't mean that physicality cannot be replaced, but
what I've experienced so far
I was not very impressed.
What if you could capture the thinking of a person?
At one point, and then compare
it to another point
and like a really beautiful
multi-complex fractal, in a way.
And ideally I'd like to kind of put two
next to each other
and compare them or talk to them.
Explore them.
And, maybe that goes a bit far.
In theory you could build the whole universe
inside a computer.
You just don't have enough power and then,
you'll never get there and it would be boring
to build the same thing all over again.
But in theory, you could, and
that's something I find kind of stunning.